I didn't really know what to make of him. He was, in those days, young, slim,
immensely energetic, and very, very knowledgeable on architectural history, which I
appreciated.
But the general impression was that there were some very interesting things to be
done in the office
and I would like to be part of them.
The job I got, which was with the British Rail Chief Architects Department,
I took the job simply to get to London basically, as a lot of people did at that
time.
and so when he made me the offer, it was one I couldn't refuse.
It was at one of our meetings and he said,
well, would you like to join us?
I can't offer you a very high salary,
but that goes without saying, Cedric.
And boy, it was not a high salary.
£1,500 a year in those days.
£63, remember.
Now that was what I was getting at the time, so effectively he said, I'll match your
salary.
Well, I was the one and only assistant.
He had a secretary, Dick Baudelaar, who was doing the technical work on the farm
palace,
the cybernetics work there, was in part of the time,
but I was the only quote-unquote architect besides Cedric.
It was immensely stimulating.
He was in and out of the office all the time.
We got in very early and as we progressed on to things,
our way of working was to chat things over when he was there.
Then he would leave drawing, drawings after drawing after drawing
and say, I think this should do that and I think this should go like this.
Particularly on the Potteries Thinkbelt.
It was a mixture of graphic and
verbal communication basically. We started this, it was, Cedric had had it in his
mind
I think for a long time and when we ceased work on the Fun Palace, the main project
because
it was being stalled by the GLC, he launched into that and what we did first of all,
I
I mean the overall concept was explained as it were, chatted through.
But we then got large scale maps of the whole area, which is quite a lot of maps
because it's quite a large area.
And we sorted out the main constituents of the plan on those ordnance survey maps.
Because we had the contours, we had the buildings.
we had practically all the information you needed. I did know the pottery
slightly because a friend of mine had gone to work as a director of the
Victoria Theatre in Stoke-on-Trent so I knew it vaguely but we worked out the
detailed implementation. The basic principle is the triangle, right?
You've got the three transfer areas, Maidley, Pittshill and Myrhor.
And then what was interesting was to sort out all the usable railway lines, of which
there were many.
There were a hell of a lot of sidings.
So these became the faculty sidings.
And then the housing, there was an awful lot of waste land.
land. So we devised four different types of housing to cope with different
locations,
different soil conditions. I mean the whole of the potteries at that time was just
one
vast excavation. There were the mines, coal mines, there was the pottery clay mines,
the
rest. The whole thing had been turned over, gouged out and over about 200 years. So
there
So there was an awful lot of interesting topography.
There were the spoil heaps, the excavations,
and there was an awful lot of just wasteland in between
where the industry had been and then gone.
So we chose our housing sites, as I said, from the Ordnance Survey maps,
and it wasn't until the thing was pretty well settled,
in my mind at least, that we went up there.
and photograph the sites which we selected.
And what was very interesting was that it was pretty well as I'd imagined it would
be,
because I knew the thing now in three dimensions, you know, from the maps.
So it was a dreadful, drizzly grey day, so that's why the photographs are dreadfully
grey and drizzly,
be in, which is no bad thing because they don't glamorise the site at all. The site
was not glamorous. It was a mucky old place then. It still is to some extent now,
but
boy was it mucky then. So we toured the whole area. We went to the transfer areas.
We looked
at the housing sites. There was nothing really that needed changing. So it was an
interesting
experiment in what you can do with just visual information which I later used as
training for
my own students when I was teaching at the AA. It's a very good discipline in fact.
How close
to realisation? Nowhere near close to realisation because it was very much you could
do this if you
had x million pounds you know. It was a demonstration thing it was not to be sold. I
mean we produced
these packages of drawings, the aerial photograph and everything, it was more a,
well it was
a response to a remark, yeah, at that time the, I think it was Lord Kent who was
Minister
in the education department and he got into a conversation and which developed into
an argument
with Cedric at some occasion talking about universities and you know Cedric said
look
you're going up the wrong path you shouldn't be doing so so Kenneth in exasperation
said well why
don't you do something and show me so he said well I will yeah but it has as I say
been in his mind
for some time. And this was therefore a demonstration of what you could do using
existing infrastructure
and a new radical way of looking at learning, looking at education as a whole life
experience.
Remember at that time, if you went to university, whether it was the new
universities or the
old ones, you stayed in student accommodation. This was Cedric's view, quite
rightly, that
housing could benefit, new housing could benefit everybody in the area and students
should
be used as a means of improving the housing stock and lifting it up and improving
expectations.
So that was a pretty radical idea at the time. It isn't now, of course, but it was
then.
The second thing was that education could be in its own right an economic driver for
a depressed area where the industry had gone.
And that of course is again today taken as granted.
If you want to push an area up you put a university in it because it's a powerhouse
for high technology and so forth.
So that was, the two things were to normalise learning, in other words, not an ivory
tower, but just part of everyday life.
Students are no different from anybody else, and everybody is a student at some time
or other through their life.
And that, together with bringing the area up by the injection of technological
change.
So those were the two linchpins.
Also, I think there was a degree of romanticism there.
The idea of using the railway lines,
which was immense fun to work out,
was an interesting comment
on how you could reuse existing infrastructure,
existing plant, existing kit,
and not junk it, basically.
So to a certain extent,
that sort of echoed Bucky's view of recycling.
The housing thing also was, it led on to various housing studies, particularly the
sprawl housing,
looking at a 25 year life housing, very low, very light footprint on the ground.
So that developed later on into the various housing studies we did.
But the four types of housing were effectively to, you know, we said this is nothing
new.
People have looked at totally enclosed, totally controlled environments.
People have looked at suburban housing.
People have looked at housing where you could slot in new units as required.
There was nothing new about that.
So the three, three, four, four, three types, sprawl, battery and crate.
That's right.
So I got it wrong.
It's not four, it's three.
Yeah.
But we chose the word sprawl because we thought it would really get up the noses of
the RIBA.
So there was a degree of bravado in there.
But it was at no time, unlike the Fun Palace, at no time did we say, you know, when
do we start building.
We costed it of course. It could have been built, of course, but it was a
demonstration project rather than,
will somebody please lend me 10 million pounds, you know,
whatever it would cost at the time.
And don't forget, we were, at the same time,
we were doing other projects.
I mean, it was fitting in with various other things.
The London Heathrow Airport Northside study,
later the Docksport building, the computer building,
and the Fun Palace pilot project,
which did look as if it had a chance of getting off the ground.
That was taken to quite a detailed degree.
So the thing was not a sit down and do it like that.
It was in the cracks, which was a nice way of working, of course,
because if you'd spent the day, as I sometimes did,
working out details of the tiling in the lavatory,
It was quite nice to go up the scale like that to one of the transfer areas.
So it was a nice mix basically, as was everything in Cedric's office.
It was always a very fruitful mix of people, ideas, the odd drink and so on and so
forth.
Very relaxed way of working.
But actually, I don't think I've ever worked so hard in my life as I did in that
office.
but that's obviously part of the magic of the place,
that you didn't want to stop working, basically.
Typical day, Alfred Place, which we moved to shortly after George Street.
And by that time, I got four rooms in Windmill Street,
which is just across Tottenham Court Road,
which I was converting to a flat with an actual bathroom,
which is the first one I'd had since I'd come to London.
So it took me three minutes to walk to the office, which was very pleasant.
Or indeed three minutes to walk home, which is more to the point.
So I would get in about nine o'clock, something like that.
Cedric would probably have been there since six.
He would have left a lot of drawings and things if he was not going to be in that
morning,
morning which is quite frequently the case or then we would go over what I was going
to do that day
or how I thought we should proceed on something and so forth. But he had so many
people coming
to see him that it was not a continuous thing. He was in and out of his little
cubbyhole office
there all the time and he would shut himself away when he was thinking which was a
very sensible
thing to do. So then we might well have a hot brandy before lunch and I would go out
either back to the flat or get a sandwich or something like that and work through.
It
was, you know, there was no particular pattern to any day, it depends what he was
doing at
the time or he might be abroad for example but there was a very close liaison on
anything we
were working i i mentioned tiles and lavatories when he was in the states at one
point i was doing
the layout for the uh the toilets lavatories call you what you want for the docks
board building
which was quite an interesting problem in its own right because i i enjoy drainage
like george
at Edmund Street who said, I'm a drains man and stench pipes are my speciality. I
enjoy
designing plumbing. It's never been the same since cast iron and copper went. It's
all
plastic now. There's no interest in designing plumbing any longer. Anyway, so he
sent a
message saying, can you send the drawings of the lavatories by email, by airmail to
me, which he did, you know, because he was, you know, it was a very close
relationship
between us in terms of detailing. Cedric had very interesting ideas on additive
detailing
which I picked up from him, basically,
because they were a sort of loose-fit approach to detailing.
I'd been trained to, or was used to doing,
classic joinery detailing,
you know, tongued in, all the rest of it there.
And Cedric's approach was a much more flexible one, in fact,
sometimes too flexible.
on the Docksport building, Frank Newby had quite rightly wanted to seal off the
plenum
space in the roof with the air conditioning in block work because that gives you an
impermeable
barrier. Cedric erupted at this because he hated the idea of what he conceived of as
an all dry building having this nasty wet dirt blocks in it. So he suggested, well
he
required that, because by that time I got an assistant to work on the actual details
through, the only time I ever had an assistant. He required that we do the cladding
of the
the plenum in pressed steel. Now that was a difficult one because you've got to make
a plenum airtight for obvious reasons and he had an unwarranted faith in the
subcontractor
being able to produce an airtight gasket seal, which was not. I didn't want to do
it, Frank
didn't want to do it he insisted it would all be perfectly right he had not
unwarranted faith
it not just in technology but in other people's use for technology cedric's
personality was
immediate and fairly overwhelming to i think to most people who met him immensely
generous and i mean he could he could talk to anybody and put anybody at their ease
basically
He was also supremely and rightly convinced of his own rightness, though he, as he
always said,
I'm always willing to admit I might be wrong.
But I think on occasions when he actually admitted he was wrong, I can count on the
fingers of one hand.
But then on the other hand, he took care to make sure he was right, because he did
his homework.
He did the research, he did the delving and the digging to get to the right
solution.
A very attractive personality, particularly to women, of which he knew many.
and the power to command an audience of as little as two or as many as a hundred
that that immense person that that's the thing that came through whenever he was
speaking he
was such an accomplished speaker the rhythm of his speech would draw the audience
along with it
It was only afterwards that you thought, hey, hang on a moment, am I sure about
that?
Why did he drink so much? Because he liked drinking.
We all drank too much at that time.
I can't say I was abstemious.
He, it kept him going.
He had three things on his desk, a box of cigars,
a bottle of brandy at a metronome.
But he liked to drink.
And at the back of his mind, I think,
there was always the feeling that it might not last that long.
Because, as you know, his father had a hereditary heart condition.
And Cedric knew he'd inherited it.
So there was always, I think, a bit of doubt in his mind about getting things done
in time.
Well, Cedric was a member of a large number of organisations, including some obscure
ones like the Hot Stuff Club, the Confederation of British Demolition Contractors,
all sorts of strange things which interested him.
interested in him. Basically he became a member of things which he wanted to know a
little
bit more about. So if you're going to build a building and expect it to be
demolished
in 25 years you might as well make sure it can be done very easily.
Hocksoff Club was a jolly get together drinking club. So there was David Alford and
Frank
Newby trying to think of the Herbert Gans, quite a lot of Americans, hard drinking
Americans,
Seoul, Kornberg. It was basically a sort of transatlantic club which included all
the
people that Cedric enjoyed talking with and exploring their minds and so forth. They
would
meet whenever one of them was in town basically, which was, you know, they were a
peripatetic
world around people. And they would meet up, it wasn't a fixed thing or anything
like that,
it was just, and it was really just a name for having a darn nice evening, lots of
good
food and good drink, you know. Well, since it's the only building I managed to put
up
for him, the Docksball building obviously because that was great fun. It was 12
months
from inception to completion. 12 months to design and build and get up a building.
That
was quite an interesting challenge. Housing research stemmed directly from one of
the
three housing types of the Thinkbelt, sprawl housing, which was originally designed
for
very uneven ground and very poor services or non-existent services. So the houses
themselves
were based on a triadic platform on jacks to accommodate for the ground because
there was
enormous subsidence going on all the time in the Thinkbelt. He walked into the
office of what was
called the regeneration department, not the planning department, and there was a big
picture
on the wall showing how much your house is likely to sink in the next five years
because
of all the mining substance. So that started off basically something you could plonk
on
ground, very lightweight, with timber frame on top. And to that we connected
self-contained
sewage digestion facilities which we got from the type of shipboard sewage digestion
which
were made by Anker at the time. And so the idea of decoupling surfaces, running them
above ground, not having to dig out dirt and put in more dirt, you know, as Bucky
put it,
started there. So we then turned this into, at the same time we were working on,
then
we were working on the steel house competition. So that provided an impetus to look
at the
flexibility which a steel frame would give us. We were looking at the ability to
customise
the outside completely. Basically the housing as it developed had a prefabricated
foundation
raft which are now pretty commonplace today which weren't then. And then you sat the
thing
on top. That was steel frame, glazed, fully air-conditioned, and you know, you could
do
almost anything with it. And it lasted 25 years because that was the optimum
financial
investment time. You could use it after that of course, but you were basically
recycling
bits of it. That was linked to, in the sort of final studies I did, particularly on
the
Tilbury study. A concept of running all the services above ground under a boardwalk
which
would also support lighting and so forth. And the roadways were aluminium emergency
runway strips, perforated aluminium. So your whole thing could be taken away after
25 years.
there was an artificial moon. An artificial moon to light it at night would go up
and
light the whole area. Which actually the way these things come round, many years
later
they were filming Sylvia, a film called Sylvia, about Sylvia Plath in our back
garden and
in our back garden and they were lighting a night scene and they had an inflatable
moon
oh god i've got a sentence to set you know it happened at last um so the housing
study
were basically looking at how you could add to existing um settlements without
placing
and demand on services and without sort of, well, investing as little as possible in
things
which would have to be left in the ground. Because the other thing we'd done is do a
study into the GLC mobile homes, which were produced in the early 60s, too, because
they
had a lot of spare bomb sites and they had a big housing shortage and they produced
rather
good timber framed mobile homes so-called mobile they were supposed to
be able to be moved from one site to another we actually followed one set of
houses being moved from one site to another they were in sections and we
were following one and the thing was bouncing along and you could see between
the floor joists and bottle after gin bottle came rolling out of the from
between the floor joists but the thing we learned from that was that the the
amount of cost factor in services is quite disproportionate the amount of
digging and laying and drainage and the rest of it made it really actually
virtually it wasn't cost effective to move these things because you had to lay
in this whole network of services if you're going to move them so that the
nozzles Bucky put it on the top was was the least of your worries in terms of
cost and I certainly ran into this later because once I after I'd left Cedric's
office I think that's right I was asked to advise the Brixton Law Centre on
on putting up a...
They were servicing Brixton Jail.
Doing a home for them, as it were.
And I did investigate using GLC mobile homes,
which were on the market at the time,
but the same problem came up, cost of services.
Site was easy, you could get a site,
but the services were the problem.
So the final bits of the housing study
were trying to decouple from the big service networks,
which effectively, we knew this because after the war,
a hell of a lot of East London was rebuilt.
But it was basically the sewers which determined the pattern of the new development,
not anything else, because you couldn't do away with them
because it would be far too expensive to change them.
So your pattern of development was constrained by your services,
which were underground.
How did he manage to be so influential?
By power of speech, by power of ideas, by power of drawings,
by opening up possibilities which people hadn't thought of before.
And remember, he had a track record very early on with the aviary.
You know, he built it, which is no small thing.
So he had credibility.
He had architectural street cred, if you like.
He wasn't just a dreamer or somebody.
He was putting forward things which could be built
and the reasons why they weren't built
were very often nothing to do with him
but with the fact that the client changed
as with the Oxford Street Corner house
where the Joe Lyons, the Salmon family changed its direction.
So clients tend to follow Cedric around.
Norman Payne, who was the chair of the British Airports Authority,
then moved to British Transport, Docksport, which is why we built the commuter
centre for him.
Geoffrey Salmon of Joe Lyons moved to another section of Joe Lyons,
and that's why the Blackpool restaurant is there, because that was their restaurant.
So it wasn't the case so much of Cedric seeking out clients as clients seeking out
Cedric.
And one thought, coming back for more.
Ah, well, Blackpool Zoo was another square building, by the way.
Cedric liked squares.
And this was Blackpool Zoo, and it was a restaurant for Blackpool Zoo.
Now, Blackpool Zoo is part of the funfair.
It's a sort of fairly curious place.
And Cedric designed the restaurant so that if it didn't get off the ground,
if it failed as a restaurant it could be converted into an animal house. The
relevance is hope,
confidence. This is a very unconfident era for architecture. Well it has been for
the
last twenty years basically. The relevance is also about having a much more
fragmented,
having a much more fragmented, flexible approach to the built environment, what we
live in.
That realising that it is never static, it's always changing, it's always renewing
itself
or being renewed, just as people are never static. And looking at built environment
as
a palimpsest of past people, which is something that very much interests me because
I did
specialize in quite a lot of historic building work. That's something you
quickly realize you are dealing with. If you've got a 500 year old building and
you can track what has happened to it, you are talking about a whole slew of
generations of people who worked, lived and changed that building, you know, which
is a very sobering thing. You're just one in that line and there will be
others beyond you. Cedric was told that he had to accommodate a folly by Peter
Smithson, Little Tower. All the drawings that Cedric produced after that showed
this thing dotting up all over the place like that, changing where it
was, whatever it was, you know. It became almost a dream set of drawings that just
said
this has appeared here but it could be there tomorrow. Look it's over there now and
all
the rest of it. And that was as his life progressed, I mean that was the change
from, you know
was initially with the Fun Palace he was designing buildings which could change. He
was more
interested in building as part of change by the end of his life. In other words, not
that
they would go anywhere, do anything, all that sort of stuff. That they would be part
of
a changing environment and adapt to it and adapt it. In other words, there should be
an interactive environment between the built works, if you like, and the people who
use
and inhabit them. And that together would form a continuously changing pattern of
living
and learning. It's very difficult to put it into words. It's a feeling more of...
Whenever
I see one of Cedric's drawings, particularly the later ones, there is that feeling
that
comes out of it is that there's a mark being put on the city here, another mark
there,
and they change, you know, they become much more impermanent.
Look at the projects, read the words, and then work out whether you like them or
not.